# 大家好 今天的月亮很園哦 我去抓點黃鱔來
Hi everyone! The moon is so round tonight. Let me catch some swamp eels.
# 現在 黃鱔都出來活動了 大晚上的
The eels are going out now, at night.
# 在這個附近田裡面
They should be nearby, in the field.
# 在那個附近田裡面就 應該就有黃鱔啦
There should be, should be some eels in the fields nearby.
# 就有沒有 好像就是鑽在這個田裡面
Any here? It seems that they squeezed into the field here.
# 在這找一 找一下
Let me search, search for while here,
# 看能不能找到一條
and see if I can get one.
# 不知道這裡下面有沒有
Would there be any here underneath?
# 哦喲 有一條
Oyo! Here's one!
# 看見沒有 看見沒有
Can you see it? Can you?
# 還想走 用 用那個燈照著它眼睛
You wanna run away? I, I'm flashing its eyes with my torch.
# 它就 走不掉
Then it, it can't run away.
# 誒呀 看見沒有
Eya! Can you see it?
# 就抓到一條
So one is caught.
# 還有沒有
Any more?
# 沒有
Nope
# 這邊也看一下
Have a look on this side too.
# 你看 這裡也有一條哦
Look! Here's another one!
# 這條 好小的
This one, is really small.
# 小的也要
But I don't mind.
# 好活潑
It's so energetic.
# 還想跑
It wants to run away.
# 你看 它這裡應該有
Look! There should be some here.
# 這裡有一條 這裡
Here's one, here.
# 這裡看到了
I can see it here.
# 看到 只看到半截身體
I see, I can only see half of its body.
# 好活潑啊 這個
It's so energetic.
# 這裡有一條 像蛇一樣的哦 一條那麼長
Here's one! It looks like a snake, you know. It's so long.
# 這樣逮到它了
So then, I've caught it.
# 沒看到了
I can't see any.
# 往下走
Let's go down there.
# 你看 這裡有一條
Look! Here's one!
# 那麼看不清楚的
It's so hard to see.
# 就看到一條尾巴 好像在這裡
I can only see a tail. It seems that it's here.
# 動都動不了
It can't even move.
# 那麼猛
It' so fierce.
# 看一下還有沒有 在這
Let me take a look and see if there are any more, here.
# 看到有一條有這裡的
I saw one here.
# 跑了
But it ran away.
# 不知道跑哪裡去了
It ran to God-knows-where-it-is,
# 鑽走了
and squeezed away.
# 這甚麼
What is it?
# 鯽魚是不是 還是 還是那個鬥魚
Is it "ji yu" (local carps)? Or, is it, I mean, fighting fish?
# 拿網來
Give me the net!
# 誒呀 撈到啦
Eya! Got it!
# 你看 這兩條
Look! These two are,
# 小鯽魚
small "ji yu".
# 那麼小的鯽魚
The "ji yu" are so small.
# 肯定是從我家池塘裡逃出來的
They must be fugitives from my pond.
# 拿桶裝 裝起來
Let me put, put them into the bucket.
# 你看 這裡有一條鯽魚哦
Look! Here's a "ji yu"
# 那麼大的鯽魚
What a huge "ji yu"!
# 誒呀 想跑
Eya! You wanna run away?
# 你看
Look!
# 這個鯽魚可以哦
This "ji yu" is not bad.
# 夠大吧 這個鯽魚
Big, isn't it? This "ji yu"
# 多裝點水來
Let me get more water.
# 你看 又一條 黃鱔
Look! Here's one more, one more eel.
# 誒呦
Eyo!
# 跑了
It ran away?
# 沒夾穩
I didn't catch it tight.
# 又看到泥鰍啦
I see a loach again.
# 這裡有條泥鰍
Here's a loach.
# 有條蚯蚓
An earthworm
# 蚯蚓也夾回去 給魚吃
Earthworm or not, I'm taking it back, for the fish.
# 跑了 跑了一條
Run away, one has run away.
# 我去看下其他地方有沒有
Let me see if there are any more at other places.
# 你看 這裡有一條
Look! Here's one.
# 你看
Look!
# 黃鱔
It's an eel.
# 那麼小
It's so small.
# 還想跑
You still wanna run away?
# 你看 這裡有一個
Look! Here's a,
# 雷頭光 (註︰沒有原字幕)
"lightning head" (local amphibian).
# 誒呦 跑得那麼快 上樹了
Eyo? It runs so fast. It's on the tree now.
# 鑽到樹上去了
It has climbed onto the tree.
# 哇 這裡一條大泥鰍哦
Wa! Here's a huge loach!
# 看到沒有
Can you see it?
# 那麼大的
It's so huge.
# 這夾子應該不好夾
I don't think the tongs can work well.
# 誒呦 抓到啦
Eyo! Got it!
# 你看 在這裡
Look! It's here.
# 這個泥鰍夠大啦
This loach is huge, isn't it?
# 又大又肥
A big fat loach
# 別跑
Don't run away!
# 把它放進桶裡面去
Let me put it into the bucket.
# 你看 就抓了那麼一點點
Look! So we've caught just a tiny little bit here.
# 兩條大鯽魚
Two big "ji yu"
# 好大呀
They're huge!
# 這些養著
I'll keep them.
# 這條泥鰍
This loach,
# 這條泥鰍好大啊 這條泥鰍
this loach is really big, this loach.
# 我們明天 明天
Tomorrow, tomorrow we'll,
# 明天再一起來把它煮掉
we'll cook them all together tomorrow.
# 做盤龍黃鱔
I'll make "Coiled Dragon Eels"!
# 好啦 現在要回去啦
Alright! We need to go back now.
# 因為都在都快十二點啦
Cuz it's nearly midnight now.
# 我們明天再搞 處理它
We'll take care of them, deal with them tomorrow.
# 我家在那裡
My home is over there.
# 把火點著來
Let me set the fire.
# 你看 這就是我們昨天抓的黃鱔
Look! These are the swamp eels that we caught yesterday night.
# 我們挑一些
Let's choose some,
# 挑一些來做那個盤龍黃鱔
choose some for your "Coiled Dragon Eels"
# 誒呀 你最小咯
Aya! You're the smallest,
# 剛好合適
and so you're perfect.
# 這種小的是剛剛好的
These small ones are perfect for our dish.
# 有好多泥鰍
There are a lot of loaches.
# 夠了
Enough,
# 就搞這些 (註︰想不到怎麼又自然又近似的說法，所以選擇自然地表達到當時的意思就算了)
enough for a dish.
# 等下我就先
You'll be the first one,
# 抓你來烤
the first one to be grilled.
# 那麼緊張幹嘛
Why are you so nervous?
# 先蓋著它
Cover it first.
# 油還沒燒熱
The oil has not yet been heated.
# 不要急
I'll take my time.
# 把這個油 倒下去
I pour the oil, into the wok.
# 這個油一定要多
It needs a lot of oil
# 好啦
Alright!
# 等一下 油燒熱啦
I'll come again, in a minute,
# 再來
when the oil is heated.
# 拿一條試一下
Let me get one and have a try.
# 可以啦 這樣就可以啦
Alright! It's alright now!
# 等下全部一起倒下去就好
I'll then pour all the rest into the wok and that's it.
# 一起卷
Let them curl up together,
# 油溫就沒那麼高啦
Then the oil won't be that hot.
# 把這個黃鱔
I'll pour the swamp eels,
# 把它倒下去然後蓋起來
pour them all into the wok and then cover it.
# 太殘忍了
It's too cruel.
# 飆的這地上上一地都是
It spills to everywhere onto the ground.
# 你看 都不卷的這個
Look! They aren't really curling up at all.
# 這個黃鱔太凄犬 太堅強啦
The eels are too stubborn, too tough.
# 我搞點料子來 把它
I'll fetch some ingredients,
# 拌一拌 這樣才好吃
and then, make a dressing. It tastes much better.
# 你看
Look!
# 全部盤在一起
They're all curling up together.
# 搞點這個配料來
Let me fetch some ingredients,
# 搞點辣椒
some chilli.
# 好啦
Alright!
# 先把這些裝起來 剛好把它們給裝起來
Let me put it into the bowl first. Put them into the bowl.
# 先放點鹽
Put some salt
# 這鹽稍微放多一點
It needs a bit more salt.
# 放點鹽 放點裝油
Put some salt, some soy sauce
# 醬油要搞多一點
I need a bit more soy sauce.
# 搞點料酒
Some cooking wine
# 嗯 我先炸一下這個 (註︰不想用"fry"，好像不太合適)
Um! Let me put it into the hot oil first.
# 炸一下之後就可以
Put it into the oil, then I can,
# 放在那上面 淋在這上面就可以吃了
put it on top, pour it on top, then it's done.
# 哇
Wa!
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 搞點這個香油 潑到這上面來
I pour the flavoured oil, onto the eels.
# 把這個
I pour the,
# 香油 淋在每一條黃鱔上
the flavoured oil, onto each eel.
# 你看 這個黃鱔
Look! This eel,
# 盤在這裡哦
it has curled up.
# 嗯
Um!
# 味道很不錯誒
It tastes really not bad.
# 很鮮嫩哦
It's so fresh and tender.
# 剛好有點辣辣的
It's also a bit spicy.
# 辣椒放少啦
I put too few chilli.
# 再多點辣椒就好啦
It would be much better with more chilli.
# 你看 它的肉可以
Look! Its meat can be,
# 你看 可以撕的哦
can be torn off.
# 一片一片的
It's in pieces,
# 可以把它撕下來
and can be torn off.
# 頭 給小狗吃
Head. Leave it for the doggies.
# 把它的內臟撕下來
Let me tear off its guts.
# 你看 這就是
Look! This is,
# 黃鱔的內臟
the gut of a swamp eel.
# 來
Come here!
# 誰要吃的
Who wants it?
# 搶
Grab it!
# 被那小狗搶走了
It's grabbed by the puppy.
# 再搞一條來
Let me get one more.
# 外焦裡嫩的
It crispy outside and tender inside.
# 你看
Look!
# 直接撕開來吃
I can tear it and eat right away.
# 這條是內臟 看
This is gut, look!
# 一下子就把它撕出來了
It can be taken out by a single pull.
# 你看 這個
Look! This is,
# 給狗吃
for the dogs.
# 小黑
Blacky!
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 這個做的
It's ah,
# 還是比較好吃的
it's really quite tasty.
# 雖然不怎麼卷
Although they don't really curl up,
# 不怎麼盤
and don't really look like a dragon,
# 但是味道好
But it tastes,
# 還是 還可以的
still, still not bad.
# 嗯 大肥狗 給一個給你吃
Um! Chubby dog, I give you a piece.
# 在你頭上
It's on your head.
# 再吃一條
I'll have one more.